<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY % defs SYSTEM "/xserver/doc/xml/xserver.ent"> %defs;
]>
  <article>

  <articleinfo>
    <!-- Title information -->
    <title>Scaled Window Support in DMX</title>
    <authorgroup>
      <author><firstname>Kevin E.</firstname><surname>Martin</surname></author>
      <author><firstname>Rickard E.</firstname><surname>Faith</surname></author>
    </authorgroup>
    <pubdate>15 October 2003 (created 19 September 2003)</pubdate>
    <releaseinfo>X Server Version &xserver.version;</releaseinfo>
    <abstract>
      <para>
      This document investigates the possibility of adding scaled window
      support to the DMX X server, thereby allowing a window or some
      selected part of the logical DMX area to be displayed using a
      scaling factor.  For example, this might allow the contents of a
      window to be magnified for easier viewing.  In particular, scaling
      for the VNC client is explored.  <emphasis remap="it">Copyright 2003
        by Red Hat, Inc., Raleigh, North Carolina</emphasis>
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </articleinfo>

      <!-- Begin the document -->
      <sect1><title>Introduction</title>
        <sect2><title>DMX</title>
          <para>
            The DMX X server (Xdmx) is a proxy server that is designed
            to allow X servers on multiple machines to be combined into
            a single multi-headed X server.  Combined with Xinerama,
            these heads can appear as a single very high-resolution
            screen.  Typical applications include the creation of a
            video wall with 16 1280x1024 displays arranged in a
            rectangle, for a total resolution of of 5120x4096.
          </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2><title>Problem Statement</title>
          <para>
            Applications displayed on a physically large video wall that
            provides high pixel-resolution may be difficult to see,
            especially if the application is designed for use on a
            typical desktop computer with a relatively small display
            located close to the human operator.  The goal of this paper
            is to describe and discuss solutions to this problem.
          </para>
          <para>
            The original driving problem for this work is to provide
            scaling for the <command>vncviewer</command> application when
            displayed using DMX (VNC scaling is currently available only
            with the Windows client, and there is no plan to extend that
            capability to other clients).  While this specific problem
            will be addressed in this paper, the general solution space
            will also be explored, since this may lead to a good
            solution not only for <command>vncviewer</command> but also for
            other applications.
          </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2><title>Task</title>
          <para>
            For reference, here is the original description of the task
            this paper addresses:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem><para>Scaled window support (for VNC)
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>
                    Investigate possibility of implementing a "scaled
                    window" extension:
                    <itemizedlist>
                      <listitem><para>
                        Add XCreateScaledWindow call that could be used
                        in place of XCreateWindow
                      </para></listitem>
                      <listitem><para>
                        All primitives drawn to scaled window would be
                        scaled by appropriate (integral?) scaling factor
                      </para></listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                  </para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>
                    Alternate approach: special case VNC support
                  </para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1><title>Previous Work</title>
        <para>
          This section reviews relevant previous work.
        </para>
        <sect2><title>VNC</title>
          <sect3><title>Scaling under VNC</title>
            <para>
              When using the <command>vncviewer</command> program for Windows, it
              is possible to specify a scaling factor (as numerator and
              denominator).  When scaling is in effect, the viewer
              software uses StretchBlt (instead of BitBlt) to display
              the pixels for the user.  When this call is made, the
              viewer already has received all of the pixel information
              (at full unscaled resolution).
            </para>
            <para>
              The scaling in VNC is primitive.  It does not conserve
              bandwidth, it does not treat textual information
              differently (i.e., by using a suitably scaled font), and
              it does not provide any anti-aliasing other than that
              provided by the underlying (Windows-only) system library.
            </para>
          </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2><title>The X Video Extension</title>
          <para>
            The X Video Extension is a widely-available extension to the
            X11 protocol that provides support for streaming video.
            Integral to this support is the ability to arbitrarily scale
            the output.  In version 2.2 of the X Video specification,
            support for scaled still images was provided, using both
            shared memory and traditional transport.  The API for this
            support uses calls that are quite similar to XCreateWindow,
            XPutImage, and XShmPutImage.  Currently, most of the drivers
            implemented in XFree86 only support data in various YUV
            formats.  However, several modern video adaptors support RGB
            as well.
          </para>
          <para>
            Note, though, that the target output for this scaling is an
            overlay plane -- so X Video provides functionality that is
            fundamentally different from that provided by the Windows
            StrechBlt call.
          </para>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1><title>Possible Solutions</title>
        <para>
          This section briefly discusses possible solutions, including
          major advantages and disadvantages from both the
          implementation and the end-user programmer standpoint.
        </para>
        <sect2><title>VNC-like Scaling</title>
          <sect3><title>Software Scaling</title>
            <para>
              The <command>vncviewer</command> application could be modified to
              provide software scaling.  This is not a general solution,
              but it does solve one of the goals of this work.
            </para>
            <para>
              A prototype of this solution was implemented and a patch
              against <filename>vnc-3.3.7-unixsrc</filename> is available in the
              <filename>dmx/external</filename> directory.  Because of limited time
              available for this work, all of the edge cases were not
              considered and the solution works well mainly for integer
              scaling.
            </para>
            <para>
              Currently, <command>vncviewer</command> writes to the X display
              with XPutImage, XCopyArea, and XFillRectangle.  All
              instances of these calls have to be aware of scaling
              and must round correctly.  In the prototype solution,
              rounding is incorrect and can cause artifacts.
            </para>
            <para>
              A better solution would be to cache all updates to the
              desktop image in <command>vncviewer</command> and only send the
              damaged area to the X display with XPutImage.  This would
              allow the damaged area to be computed so that rounding
              errors do not create artifacts.  This method is probably
              similar to what is used in the Window client.  (The whole
              VNC suite is being re-written in C++ and the forthcoming
              version 4 has not been evaluated.)
            </para>
          </sect3>
          <sect3><title>Scaling with the X Video Extension</title>
            <para>
              The scaling in the Windows <command>vncviewer</command> application
              makes use of a scaled blit that is supplied by the
              underlying system library.  Several video cards currently
              provide support for a scaled blit, and some X servers
              (including XFree86) expose this capability to applications
              via the XvPutImage interface of the X Video Extension.
              The capability exposed by XvPutImage results in the scaled
              image being drawn to an overlay plane.  Most video cards
              also provide support for a scaled blit into the normal
              output planes, but this is not exposed via XvPutImage.
            </para>
            <para>
              The <command>vncviewer</command> program could be modified to use
              the X Video Extension to provide scaling under X11 that is
              similar to the scaling currently provided under Windows.
              Unfortunately, Xdmx does not currently export the X Video
              Extension, so this would not provide an immediate solution
              usable with DMX.
            </para>
            <para>
              A very early-stage proof-of-concept prototype was
              implemented and a preliminary patch against
              <filename>vnc-3.3.7-unixsrc</filename> is available in the
              <filename>dmx/external</filename> directory.  This prototype was
              implemented to better understand the problems that must be
              solved to make this solution viable:
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                  As noted under the software scaling section above,
                  <command>vncviewer</command> writes to the X display with
                  several different calls.  These calls write to the
                  normal output planes and are compatible with
                  XvPutImage, which writes to an overlay plane.  To
                  eliminate artifacts caused by this problem,
                  <command>vncviewer</command> should be modified so that a cached
                  copy of the desktop is available, either as a
                  client-side image or a server-side off-screen pixmap,
                  so that XvPutImage would be the only method for
                  writing to the X display.
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Although several modern graphics adaptors support
                    hardware scaling using an RGB format (e.g., ATI
                    Radeon, nVidia, etc.), XFree86 drivers typically
                    only implement YUV formats.  YUV generally compress
                    the pixel information in some way.  For example, two
                    commonly implemented formats, YUY2 and UYVY provide
                    intensity information for every RGB pixel, but only
                    provide chroma and luminance information for pairs
                    of horizontal pixels.  Since VNC uses
                    pixel-resolution for communicating updates on the
                    wire, additional artifacts are introduced (because
                    there may not be enough information from the wire to
                    update a pair of pixels).
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    Further, the well-known problem with YUV encoding
                    is even more evident when the image is a desktop
                    instead of a movie.  For example, consider a
                    1-pixel-wide vertical window border.  If the border
                    changes in color but not intensity (e.g., because a
                    window manager uses color to indicate focus), there
                    may or may not be a change in the YUY2 image,
                    depending on the algorithm used for RGB to YUV
                    conversion and on how the border pixel is ordered in
                    the pair of pixels used by the algorithm.
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    Many of these artifacts could be eliminated if
                    <command>vncviewer</command> cached a complete RGB image of
                    the desktop, and only did the conversion to YUV for
                    properly aligned areas of damage.  The remaining artifacts
                    could be eliminated if an RGB format was used with X
                    Video (which may require the extension of existing
                    XFree86 drivers to support RGB).
                  </para>
	        </listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                  Most modern video cards support exactly one overlay
                  plane that is suitable for use with X Video.
                  Therefore, only one application can use X Video at any
                  given time.  This is a severe limitation in a desktop
                  environment.
                </para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <sect4><title>Implementing the X Video Extension for DMX</title>
              <para>
                The user-level API for X Video is fairly simple, but the
                underlying support required for the full specification
                is large.  However, since the API provides a method to
                query supported capabilities, a usable subset of X
                Video can be implemented that would support XvPutImage
                and little else.  This would require support for the
                following:
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>
                    X Video Extension API calls, including the
                    following:
                    <itemizedlist>
                      <listitem><para>XvQueryExtension</para></listitem>
                      <listitem><para>XvQueryAdaptors</para></listitem>
                      <listitem><para>XvQueryPortAttributes</para></listitem>
                      <listitem><para>XvFreeAdaptorInfo</para></listitem>
                      <listitem><para>XvListImageFormats</para></listitem>
                      <listitem><para>XvGrabPort</para></listitem>
                      <listitem><para>XvCreateImage</para></listitem>
                      <listitem><para>XvPutImage</para></listitem>
                      <listitem><para>XvShmCreateImage</para></listitem>
                      <listitem><para>XvShmPutImage</para></listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
                  </para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>
                    Support for querying back-end X Video Extension
                    capabilities.
                  </para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>
                    Support for sending the image to the back-ends.
                    Because X Video requires sending full images, there
                    may be a trade-off between bandwidth limitations and
                    additional complexity to divide the image up such
                    that is scales properly.
                  </para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>
                    Possible support for a software fall-back.  For
                    example, if all of the back-ends do not support the X
                    Video Extension, software scaling can be implemented
                    such that the image is sent to the back-end with
                    XPutImage.  This pathway would have poor
                    performance.
                  </para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </para>
            </sect4>
            <sect4><title>Supporting RGB formats for the X Video Extension</title>
              <para>
                Assuming an XFree86 driver already supports the X Video
                Extension, and assuming the target hardware supports an
                RGB format, then adding support for that format is
                relatively simple and straightforward.
              </para>
            </sect4>
          </sect3>
          <sect3><title>Scaling with an XPutImageScaled Extension</title>
            <para>
              Instead of (or in addition to) implementing the X Video
              Extension in DMX, one obvious solution would be to
              implement a new extension that provides access to
              hardware-assisted scaled blits, similar to the StretchBlt
              call available under Windows.  This call would scale RGB
              images and would not use the overlay plane (unlike the X
              Video Extension).
            </para>
            <para>
              This approach has many of the same advantages and
              disadvantages as the XCopyAreaScaled Extension, discussed
              in the next section.  Discussion of XPutImageScaled is
              deferred in favor of XCopyAreaScaled for the following
              reasons:
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                  XPutImageScaled can be emulated with XCopyAreaScaled
                  by first using XPutImage to copy the image to an
                  off-screen pixmap, and then calling XCopyAreaScaled
                  between that off-screen pixmap and the target
                  drawable.
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                  Since XCopyAreaScaled would copy between two areas of
                  on-screen or off-screen memory, it has additional uses
                  and can be viewed as efficiently providing a superset
                  of XPutImageScaled functionality.
                </para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </sect3>
          <sect3><title>Scaling with an XCopyAreaScaled Extension</title>
            <para>
              As noted in the previous section, because XCopyAreaScaled
              provides a superset of the functionality provided by
              XPutImageScaled, we will consider this extension instead.
            </para>
            <para>
              First, XCopyAreaScaled would provide for RGB scaling
              between pixmaps (i.e., on-screen or off-screen areas of
              memory that reside on the video card).  Unlike the X Video
              Extension, which writes into an overlay plane,
              XCopyAreaScaled would write into the non-overlay areas of
              the screen.  Key points to consider are as follows:
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                  Because different planes are involved, the two scaling
                  operations are usually implemented in hardware
                  differently, so an XCopyAreaScaled extension could be
                  added in a manner that would neither conflict with nor
                  interact with the X Video extension in any way.
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                  The XCopyAreaScaled extension provides new
                  functionality that the X Video Extension does not
                  provide.  Based on anecdotal feedback, we believe that
                  many people outside the DMX and VNC communities would
                  be excited about this extension.
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                  The main drawback to this extension is that it is new
                  and needs to be implemented at the driver level in
                  XFree86 for each video card to be supported.  At the
                  present time, it is more likely that the X Video
                  Extension will be implemented for a particular piece
                  hardware because the X Video extension has multimedia
                  uses.  However, over time, we would expect the
                  XCopyAreaScaled extension to be implemented along with
                  the X Video extension, especially if it becomes
                  popular.
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                  Another drawback is that not all modern cards provide
                  support for a simple scaled blit operation.  However,
                  these cards usually do provide a 3D pipeline which
                  could be used to provide this functionality in a
                  manner that is transparent to the client application
                  that is using the XCopyAreaScaled extension.  However,
                  this implementation pathway would make this extension
                  somewhat more difficult to implement on certain cards.
                </para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </sect3>
          <sect3><title>Scaling with OpenGL</title>
            <para>
              Another general solution to the scaling problem is to use
              the texture scaling found in all 3D hardware.  This
              ability is already exposed through OpenGL and can be
              exploited by clients without X server modification (i.e.,
              other than the ability to support OpenGL).  An application
              using OpenGL would transmit the non-scaled image to the X
              server as a texture, and would then display a single
              non-transformed rect using that texture.  This also works
              around the single overlay problem with the X Video
              Extension as well as the need to implement additional
              scaled primitive extensions.
            </para>
            <para>
              The downside is that most OpenGL implementations require
              power of 2 texture sizes and this can be very wasteful of
              memory if, for example, the application needs to scale a
              1025x1025 image, which would require a 2048x2048 texture
              area (even a 640x480 image would require a 1024x512
              texture).  Another downside is that some OpenGL
              implementations have a limited about of texture memory and
              cannot handle textures that are very large.  For example,
              they might limit the texture size to 1024x1024.
            </para>
          </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2><title>Application-transparent Scaling for DMX
          </title><sect3><title>Back-end Scaling Without Disconnect/Reconnect</title>
            <para>
              VNC does scaling on the client side (in the
              <command>vncviewer</command> application).  Implementing a similar
              solution for DMX would require support in the back-end X
              servers and, therefore, is not a general solution.
            </para>
            <para>
              XFree86 already implements some support for "scaling" that
              could be used with DMX: if, in the XF86Config file,
              multiple Modes are listed in the Display Subsection of the
              Screen Section, then pressing Ctrl-Alt-Plus and
              Ctrl-Alt-Minus can be used to iterate through the listed
              modes.  The display dimensions will change to the
              dimensions in the Modes line, but the logical dimensions
              of the X server (i.e., the dimensions that Xdmx knows
              about) will not change.
            </para>
            <para>
              Further, the dimensions of the XFree86 display are under
              software control (via the XFree86-VidModeExtension), so
              the Xdmx server could change the screen dimensions on a
              per-display basis, thereby scaling the information on part
              of that display.
            </para>
            <para>
              However, this scaling appears to have limited use.  For
              example, assume a 4 by 4 display wall consisting of 16
              1280x1024 displays.  If all of the back-end servers were
              simultaneously configured to display 640x480, the left
              hand corner of each display would be magnified, but the
              composite result would be unreadable.  Magnifying one
              display at a time could be usable, but could have limited
              utility, since the result would still be no larger than a
              single display.
            </para>
          </sect3>
          <sect3><title>Back-end Scaling With Disconnect/Reconnect</title>
            <para>
              Disconnect and reconnect features are not currently
              supported in DMX, but are scheduled to be implemented in
              the future.  These features, combined with the
              XFree86-VidModeExtension Extension, would allow an
              application to do the following:
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>
                  Disconnect a specific back-end server (via the DMX
                  Extension),
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                  reconfigure the XFree86 back-end server resolution,
                  and
                </para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>
                  reconnect the back-end server to DMX -- at a new
                  origin with the new screen resolution.
                </para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
              For example, consider a display wall consisting of 16
              1280x1024 displays with a total resolution of 5120x4096.
              All of the screens could be disconnected, repositioned,
              and reconnected each at a resolution of 640x480.  The
              total resolution of the display wall would be 2560x1920,
              allowing a view of a selected area approximately
              one-fourth of the size of the DMX display.  This change
              would be completely application independent (except,
              perhaps, for a DMX-aware window manager).  When work at
              the increased resolution was completed, the back-end
              servers could be disconnected, reconfigured, and
              reconnected for the original 5120x4096 view.
            </para>
            <para>
              Support for this type of scaling can be implemented in a
              DMX-aware X11 client assuming the DMX server support
              arbitrary disconnect and reconnect semantics.  Because
              this application cannot be written before
              disconnect/reconnect is implemented, this solution will
              not be discussed further in this paper.
            </para>
          </sect3>
          <sect3><title>Server-side Scaling</title>
            <para>
              In earlier versions of DMX, a frame buffer was maintained
              on the server side, and XPutImage was used to move the
              information from the server to the client (similar to some
              early VNC implementations).  The use of a server-side
              frame buffer would allow the server to do scaling, but is
              not a recommended solution because of overall performance
              issues and server-side memory issues (i.e., the frame
              buffer would be very large for large display walls).
            </para>
            <para>
              Exploration of this path is not recommended.
            </para>
          </sect3>
        </sect2>
        <sect2><title>XCreateScaledWindow API</title>
          <para>
            The implementation of X Video Extension in DMX, and the use
            of XvPutImage by applications requiring scaling requires
            significant changes in DMX Further, XvPutImage is,
            essentially a scaled blit, and it is only useful for
            applications which are already using (or can be modified to
            use) XPutImage.  Therefore, a more general API will be
            discussed as another possibility.
          </para>
          <para>
            X applications typically create windows with the
            XCreateWindow call.  A new extension could provide an
            XCreateScaledWindow call that could be used in place of the
            XCreateWindow call and be otherwise transparent to the
            application.  This would allow applications, even those that
            do not depend on XPutImage, to take advantage of window
            scaling.  In this section we describe how the call would
            work, what transparency it provides, and how to solve the
            potential problems that transparency creates.
          </para>
          <sect3><title>XCreateWindow</title>
            <para>
              The XCreateWindow call takes width and height as
              parameters.  An XCreateScaledWindow call could take all
              the same parameters, with the addition of a scaling factor.
            </para>
          </sect3>
          <sect3><title>XSetWindowAttributes</title>
            <para>
              An X11 window has several attributes that would have to be
              scaled:
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>Background and border pixmaps</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Border width</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Cursor</para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para>
          </sect3>
          <sect3><title>XGetWindowAttributes, XGetGeometry</title>
            <para>
              For transparency, calls that query the window attributes
              should return unscaled information.  This suggests that
              all unscaled pixmaps and window attributes should be
              cached.
            </para>
            <para>
              Unfortunately, a window manager requires the scaled
              geometry to properly decorate the window.  The X server
              can probably determine which client is acting as the
              window manager (e.g., because that client will select
              events that are used exclusively by the window manager).
              However, other Scaled Window Extension aware clients may
              also need to determine the scaled geometry.  Therefore, at
              least two additional extension calls should be
              implemented: XGetScaledWindowAttributes and
              XGetScaledGeometry.
            </para>
          </sect3>
          <sect3><title>Popup and Child window positions</title>
            <para>
              Some applications may position popup and child windows
              based on an unscaled notion of the main window geometry.
              In this case, additional modifications to the client would
              be required.
            </para>
          </sect3>
          <sect3><title>Events</title>
            <para>
              Most events (e.g., for mouse motion) return information
              about the coordinates at which the even occurred.  These
              coordinates would have to be modified so that unscaled
              values were presented to the client.
            </para>
          </sect3>
          <sect3><title>Implementation</title>
            <para>
              There are many implementation issues, some of which are
              similar to the issues involved in implementing the X Video
              Extension for DMX.  The window contents must be scaled,
              either by performing all operations to a frame buffer and
              then writing the image to the display (perhaps using
              hardware scaling support), or by modifying all of the
              various drawing operations to perform scaling.  Because of
              the complexity involved, the frame buffer option is
              recommended.
            </para>
          </sect3>
        </sect2>
      </sect1>

      <sect1><title>Conclusion and Recommendations
        </title><para>
          We recommend a three phase implementation strategy, based on
          how an application could be written to take advantage of
          scaling:
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The XCopyAreaScaled extension should be implemented, since
                this is the ideal solution for applications like VNC, and
                since making use of this extension will require minimal
                changes to applications that already use XPutImage or
                XCopyArea.
              </para>
              <para>
                The initial implementation work would include the design
                of the X protocol extension, writing this up in the
                usual format for extension documentation, implementation
                of the protocol transport pieces in XFree86,
                implementation of a software fall-back in XFree86 and
                DMX, one example hardware implementation for XFree86,
                and implementation of support for this extension in DMX.
              </para>
              <para>
                We suggest implementing the extension first on the ATI
                Radeon cards.  However, since these cards do not provide
                a 2D scaled blit primitive, the implementation would
                have to make use of the 3D texture engine to emulate a
                scaled blit.  This is recommended, since other modern
                graphics cards also do not provide a simple 2D scaled
                blit operation and an example of the more difficult
                implementation pathway would be helpful to others.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Until XCopyAreaScaled is widely supported, applications
                that require scaling will have to fall back to another
                scaling method.  We suggest OpenGL as the first fall-back
                method because it is widely available and supported by
                DMX.
              </para>
              <para>
                A project centered around OpenGL-based scaling would
                implement this scaling in VNC as an example.  This work
                would include re-writing the <command>vncviewer</command>
                rendering engine to cache a master copy of the desktop
                image for all operations.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Since OpenGL is not implemented everywhere, and may not
                provide hardware-assisted performance in every
                implementation, an application that requires scaling
                should also fall back to using the X Video Extension.
              </para>
              <para>
                This project would add support for the X Video Extension
                to DMX and would add support to VNC to take advantage of
                this extension without introducing artifacts.  This
                would require modifying the <command>vncviewer</command> rendering
                engine to cache a master copy of the desktop image for
                all operations.  This project should also add support
                for the RGB format to at least one XFree86 driver (e.g.,
                ATI Radeon).
              </para>
              <para>
                The X Video Extension is one of the few popular
                extensions that DMX does not support.  We recommend
                implementing the X Video Extension even if scaling is
                the specific goal of that work.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
          We do <emphasis>not</emphasis> recommend implementation of the
          XCreateScaledWindow extension because of the complexity
          involved.  We do <emphasis>not</emphasis> recommend implementation of the
          XPutImageScaled extension because it requires the same amount
          of work as the XCopyAreaScaled extension, but provides less
          functionality.  Further, server-side scaling with a large
          frame buffer is <emphasis>not</emphasis> recommended because of the
          performance implications.
        </para>
        <para>
          The back-end scaling, especially with disconnect/reconnect
          support should be explored in the future after
          disconnect/reconnect is implemented, but not at the present
          time.
        </para>
      </sect1>

  </article>
  <!-- Local Variables: -->
  <!-- fill-column: 72  -->
  <!-- End:             -->
