<chapter>
<title>Acknowledgments</title>

<para>
Many thanks go to Ralph Swick (Project Athena / Digital) who has
contributed much time and effort to this widget set.  Previous
versions of the widget set are largely due to his time and effort.
Many of the improvements that I have been able to make are because he
provided a solid foundation to build upon.  While much of the effort
has been Ralph's, many other people have contributed to the code.
</para>

<literallayout class="monospaced">
Mark Ackerman (formerly Project Athena)
Donna Converse (MIT X Consortium)
Jim Fulton (formerly MIT X Consortium)
Loretta Guarino-Reid (Digital WSL)
Charles Haynes (Digital WSL)
Rich Hyde (Digital WSL)
Mary Larson (Digital UEG)
Joel McCormack (Digital WSL)
Ron Newman (formerly Project Athena)
Jeanne Rich (Digital WSL)
Terry Weissman (formerly Digital WSL)
</literallayout>

<para>
While not much remains of the X10 toolkit, many of the ideas for this
widget set come from that original version.  The design and
implementation of the X10 toolkit were done by:
</para>

<literallayout class="monospaced">
Mike Gancarz (formerly Digital UEG)
Charles Haynes (Digital WSL)
Phil Karlton (formerly Digital WSL)
Kathleen Langone (Digital UEG)
Mary Larson (Digital UEG)
Ram Rao (Digital UEG)
Smokey Wallace (formerly Digital WSL)
Terry Weissman (formerly Digital WSL)
</literallayout>

<para>
I have used the formatting ideas, and some of the words from previous
versions of this document.  The X11R3 Athena widget document was written by:
</para>

<literallayout class="monospaced">
Ralph R. Swick (Project Athena/ Digital)
Terry Weissman (formerly Digital WSL)
Al Mento (Digital UEG)
</literallayout>

<para>
Putting this manual together was a major task in and of itself.  I
would like to thank Ralph Swick, Donna Converse, and Jim Fulton for
taking the time to help convert my technical knowledge into legible
text.  A special thanks to Jean Diaz (O'Reilly and Associates) for
spending nearly a month with me working out all the annoying little
details.
</para>

<literallayout class="monospaced">
Chris D. Peterson
MIT X Consortium 1989
</literallayout>

<para>
The R5 edition of this document has been edited by the research staff of
the MIT X Consortium, with significant contributions by Jim Fulton (NCD).
</para>

<literallayout class="monospaced">
Donna Converse
MIT X Consortium 1991
</literallayout>

<para>
The R6 edition of this document has been edited to reflect changes
brought about by research staff of the Omron Corporation, with special
recognition to Li Yuhong, Seiji Kuwari, and Hiroshi Kuribayashi for
the X11R5/contrib/lib/Xaw internationalization that inspired this version.
</para>
<literallayout class="monospaced">
Frank Sheeran
Omron Corporation 1994
</literallayout>

</chapter>
